Hello everyone, welcome to the
cardiovascular
physiology lectures.
I am Dr. Sepulvina
and today I will
be teaching you about
molecular physiology
of vascular smooth
muscle cells.
So as the name per
se is saying, we
are going to discuss
about muscle,
vascular smooth muscle
cells. So muscle as a
basic function is to contract
and relax, and that's
what we are going to
discuss in this lecture.
So we have four learning
objectives for this
lecture, and briefly what
we are going to discuss is
how these specific type
of muscle cells contract,
what is essential
for the mechanism of
contraction and relaxation
that will result
in vasodilation or
vasoconstriction.
And we will discuss
about this mechanism
how they are
depending on calcium.
So, calcium is a crucial
ion that play a role in
vascularist movements of cells
contraction and relaxation.
And the vascularist movements
of cells is these cells
in the vasculature that
have as a basic function
contract and relax.
If for any reason these
cells start to do something
else, that tell us that the
cell is undergoing an unhealth
situation, a pathological
situation. For example,
in the event that the
vascular immune muscle
cells, for example, start
to produce collagen,
that is a strong indication
that something very bad
is going on because these
type of the cells are not
supposed to produce collagen
or extracellular proteins.
basically the cells
are healthy if
they are only
contract and relaxing.
And during this
lecture also we will
mention some type of
pathological conditions
where the vascular
smooth muscle cells
lose their native phenotype
from contractile become,
for example, proliferative
or synthetic cells.
So, vascular smooth
muscle cells is known to
be spindle-shaped cells.
So, here in the left,
you can see vascular
smooth muscle cells that
we have isolated in my
lab from mice aortas.
and even in culture cells
you can see that these
cells has they can
maintain the spindle shape
this is very different
from the endothelial
cells as you have your
previous lectures you saw
that endothelial cells
are more round and small
cells and when we compare
to the smooth muscle
cells It's totally
different. It's a bigger
cell, spindle shape, and
have a single nucleus.
Here in the right,
you have the cells
in culture. You see
in blue the nucleus
of the cells and
in green acting.
That is one of the key
contractile proteins.
So basically, we
can see that these
cells have a lot
contractile proteins.
So, the basic characteristics
of vascular smooth
muscle cells is that those
cells are not estriated
compared to skeletal muscle and
cardiac muscle
that are estriated.
They are not organized in
sarcomators and they don't
have troponin. Troponin is
exclusively in the cardiac
muscle, and in the smooth
muscles, we have calmodulin.
The native phenotype
of vascular smooth
muscle cells is
contractile phenotype.
And also, this type
of the cells don't
have Z-discs. They
have dense bodies.
and one of the important
characteristics of this
type of the cells is one
of them cells that have
more plasticity they can
like become another type
of the cells so from a
contractile native phenotype
these cells can be
converted in for example
osteoblastic cells,
synthetic and proliferative,
phagocytic cells.
So these smooth muscle
cells have this property of
change and when they change
is usually an indication
that a pathological
condition is taking place.
So here we have a side
by side, a normal and I
will call disease or
unhealthy vascularized
muscle cells. So how we
can identify when these
cells are healthy and
when they are unhealthy?
So health one, they have
a spindle shape, they have
contractile property, and
they are not proliferative.
That means these cells are
not supposed to proliferate.
They are supposed only
to contract and relax and
also they don't migrate
so smooth muscle cells is
located in the blood vessels
in the middle layer and in
a event that these cells
become unhealth they can
migrate for example for the
looming of the blood vessel.
Here we have the
representation in this
figure when the smooth
muscle cells become
unhealthy. You can see
they change the shape,
they start to produce factors
and release those factors.
As an example, they
can produce collagen,
astrocellular matrix proteins.
So they have more round
shape and they start
to produce and secrete
substance and they
will proliferate and
also migrate. They
will invade the looming
of the blood vessel.
So here we have one
example when the
vascular smooth muscle
cells are unhealthy.
So here are arteries from pre
-diabetic and diabetic animals.
Those are rats. So whatever
you see in red color
are reactive oxygen
species. So vascular smooth
muscle cells, again I
will stress about that,
it's not supposed to
produce reactive oxygen
species. It's just supposed
to contract and relax.
If the cell is producing
reactive oxygen species,
it's because something is
not going well. And yes,
this is a diabetic artery.
We know that in diabetes
we have endothelial
dysfunction and also we
have a high production of
reactive oxygen species.
So, as we are here
discussing about what is a
normal, what is a disease
or unhealthy vascular smooth
muscle cells, one process
that involves unhealthy
vascular smooth muscle
cells are atherosclerotic
disease. So, during
atherosclerosis progression,
we will start to
observe the presence of
unhealth vascular
smooth muscle cells.
And one of the alternative
approaches to treat
atherosclerosis.
So, here we have the
representation of a
blood vessels with a
atherosclerotic plaque
that is blocking the
looming of the vessels.
One way to treat, for
example, a patient undergoing
this process is
implantation of a stent,
that is this metal device
that is introduced in
the artery in order to
keep this looming open.
One of the negative,
let's say, one of the
potential negative
side effects or consequence
of this procedure
is that this stent,
this metal device,
they can damage the
endothelial cells.
and when we damage
endothelial cells we will have
less production of nitric
oxide and nitric oxide is
not only a vasodilator
but is also an anti
-proliferative factor so every
time we have nitric oxide
we can have vasodilation
but also we will protect
the neighbor cells in this
case the vascular smooth
muscle cells. It's an
anti-proliferative factor.
In this situation, if we
damage the endothelial,
we will have less nitric
oxide and the vascular
smooth muscle cells
start to proliferate and
start to migrate and that
can cause re-stenosis.
So here is one of the
examples where we have this
cross-talking between
endothelial cells and vascular
smooth muscle cells and
the smooth muscle cells
is the one in this case
responsible for the re
-stenosis that make this
looming be closed again.
Another very important
role of the vascular
smooth muscle cells
in atherosclerosis
is when we have the plaque
rupture that is very life
-threatening situation
for a patient that suffer
from atherosclerotic disease
and as you can see in
this figure so here we have
very small in gray color
the endothelial cells and
then this whole pink is
the vascular smooth muscle
cells So, the vascular
smooth muscle cells lost
the contractile phenotype
during this atherosclerotic
disease. And these cells,
the vascular smooth
muscle cells, start to
produce interleucines,
inflammatory factors,
metalloproteases,
collagen, and other factors
that will contribute
for the rupture of the
atherosclerotic plaque.
So this is one example
where vascular smooth muscle
cells play a role during
atherosclerotic disease and how
is it because these cells
again lose the contractile
phenotype, become synthetic,
they change the phenotype
and start to produce all
these factors that will play
a key role in breaking this
atherosclerotic plaque.
Okay, so let's do some
practical questions to
see if we can consolidate
some of these concepts
that we have discussed
until now about health
and unhealth vascular
smooth muscle cells.
i know it's very early
there is still a long way
to go for boards but i
like to introduce in my
lecture some questions not
only relate to questions
that will be asking the
boards but those are
questions that i consider
good to go over the
basic concepts of vascular
physiology in general.
So let's do it. So a
59 years old man become
unconscious after experienced
severe chest pain. He
has a history of smoking
and dyslipidemia, but
is no compliant with his
prescribed medication.
The man is pronounced dead on
arrival to the emergency room.
An autopsy reveals
diffuse atherosclerotic
vascular disease involving
the coronary arteries.
One of the atheromatosis
plaque in the left
main artery has a
ruptured fibrose cap.
with an overlying
occluding thrombus.
Which of the following
cellular components
is most directly
involved in formation of
the fibrous portion of
the patient's plaque?
Well, the right answer
here is smooth muscle cells
because these are the
cells that is changing the
phenotype and is producing all
the factors that contribute
for the formation of the
fibrous portion of the
plaque and the break, the
rupture of this plaque.
So,
the structure of the
vascular smooth muscle
cells basically are
contractile proteins, And we
have two many contractile
proteins, actin and
myosin. So, if you see
here in this figure, we
have the actin in purple
is the thin filament.
And in green, we have
the thick filaments,
that's myosin. So,
basically, those are the
proteins responsible
for the contraction and
relaxation. We have some
intermediary filaments,
but the main ones
are actin and myosin.
And we can see these dense
bodies that are located in
the cytoplasma, but also
here close to the membrane.
And they are interconnected
with the actin and myosin.
So, here we have the
representation of
the vascular smoothness
of cells in the
relaxed stage and
contractile stage.
So, in the relaxed stage,
they have this spindle shape.
And here we can see in
blue is the actin filament.
And in red color with
some heads is the myosin.
So, the myosin needs to
interact with actin in
order to have contraction,
and how this happens is
the head of the myosin
needs to be phosphorylated.
So, now if we go for
this figure, we can see
that the head of the
myosin is interacting
with the actin, so they
slide against each other,
and then the contractile
process happens.
And the key information
here is how this happens
is because the head
of the myosin becomes
phosphorylated. So
phosphorylation of myosin
is crucial for the
initiation of contraction.
This is just a detail,
but I think it's important
to mention that it has
been demonstrated that the
smooth muscle cells have
these specific invaginations
in the plasmatic
membrane. And what we have
in these invaginations are
usually the main receptors
that will play a
contraction and relaxation.
And also we have the
sarcoplasmic
reticulum, that is a
place where we store calcium.
So this invagination in
vascular smooth muscle
cells is very important.
It's not just a shape,
but it's a region where
we can find sarcoplasmatic
reticulum that's full of
calcium and receptors.
Here in the right we
have the representation
of a cross-section of
a blood vessel, artery.
So you can see here
in gray color is
representing the
endotelium and in red
color is vascular
smooth muscle cells.
So, the nerves ending
in the vasculous
movements of cells
are noradrenergic,
so norepinephrine.
Norepinephrine will
bind in specific
receptors here, alpha
-1, alpha-2 adrenergic
receptors, and will
cause contraction.
And just as a review,
because you already have
the endothelial cells
lectures, the nerves
that come to the
endothelial cells are the
cholinergic ones. So, instead
of release norepinephrine,
they will be releasing
acetylcholine.
And you remember,
acetylcholine will bind to
muscarinic receptors in the
endothelial cells and will
produce nitric oxide
resulting in mesodilation.
So the smooth muscle
cells is an involuntary
muscle. We cannot
control this muscle.
It's controlled basically by
the autonomic nervous system.
This type of muscle,
they can remain contract
for a long period of
time. they have no fatigue
and something that's
very unique about smooth
muscle cells is that
they can initiate its
own contraction independent
of a neurotransmitter
or hormones and that
we call myogenic tone.
Myogenic tone is this
phenomenon that the smooth
muscle can contract and
relax just under mechanical
stimulus that doesn't
need norepinephrine this
doesn't involve hormones
like endothelium 2 endothelin
it's just physical so
where we can observe
myogenic tone in resistant
vessels one classical example
of resistant vessel is
mesenteric arteries so
if you see here in the
bottom, we have isolate
mesenteric arteries, and when
we increase the intraluminal
pressure, that will
cause vasoconstriction.
And when we decrease
the intraluminal
pressures, that will
cause vasodilation.
So we can do this in the
lab applying pressure
in the looming of
the artery, but this
also happens in our
body when, let's say,
we have increase of
blood pressure, we
have an increase here
in the intraluminal
pressure that will
cause vasoconstriction.
So here we have the schematic
figure of this process.
So, we have an increase
in intraluminal pressure
that will cause a tension
in the receptors in the
membrane of vascular smooth
muscle cells that will
lead to depolarization.
Then we have increase
of influx of calcium,
and then we will
have the contraction.
Here is neural control of
vascular smooth
muscle cells. So,
the vascular smooth muscle
cells usually will contract
in the presence of
neurotransmitter or hormones.
Or in the absence of that, we
will have the myogenic tone.
So, here we have the
vascular smooth muscle cells
and here we have the
nerves that is releasing
norepinephrine. Norepinephrine
can bind in two receptors,
alpha-1 adrenergic or
alpha-2 adrenergic.
One or the other will
lead to contraction.
The difference is that
they use different pathways
and the most important
receptor is alpha-1.
Alpha-2 has effect
but is very minimum.
So when norepinephrine
binds to alpha-1 adrenergic
receptor that will
activate ip3 that will open
this channel that's
located in the sarcoplasmic
reticulum so here you
can see er so this was my
mistake it's not er is sr so
it's sarcoplasmic reticulum,
that is this structure
that stores calcium.
So, when IP3 binds
to this receptor,
we have the open, and
then all the calcium
stored here is released in the
cytoplasm, and then we
have the contraction.
But if you're not epinephrine
bind in the alpha-2
adrenergic receptor. They
will cause a decrease in
cyclic AMP and that also
will lead to contraction.
So now we will focus in
the alpha one because
this is the predominant
receptor responsible
for contraction in the
presence of norepinephrine.
And here we can see
that it has increase of
calcium.
What is the next step for the
vascular smooth
muscle cells contract?
So, after we have this
increase of calcium,
it can be,
for example, any epinephrine
bind to alpha-1, IP3,
activate the channel
in sarcoplasmic
reticulum, increase calcium.
Here is another mechanism
when we have the
depolarization and then open
the voltage gate calcium
channel, so the calcium
enter so now we have a lot
calcium in the cell and
then calcium will bind to
calmodulin very very
important to remember this is
board questions calmodulin
is very specific of
vascular smooth muscle cells
so calmodulin is a protein
that have four arms and
each arm can bind one
calcium. So, one calmodulin
can have four calcium.
When we have the formation
of this complex calcium
-calmodulin, this complex
will activate this kinase,
this enzyme called myosin
light chain kinase.
And when this
enzyme is activated,
they will phosphorylate myosin.
Once myosin is phosphorylated,
they can interact
with actin and then the
contraction will happen.
So, very important message
that we are taking here
from this slide is that,
first, I hope I have convinced
you that calcium is
crucial. We need calcium in
order to have contraction
of vascular smooth muscle
cells. we need calmodulin and
then we need phosphorylate
the head of myosin so
without those events we
cannot have contraction and
remember if the protein is
phosphorylated should have
a way to dephosphorylate
this protein and who this
phosphorylate is the myosin
light chain phosphatase.
This enzyme will remove
the phosphorylation
and then will happen
the opposite, you
have relaxation.
So here is just a detail
showing that the head
of the myosin can be
phosphorylated and that will
interact with actin and
cause the contraction.
In summary, we can see
that for the vascular
smooth muscle cells
contract, we need increase of
the calcium intracellular,
formation of the
calcium comodulin
complex that will lead to
activation of the myosin
light chain kinase that will
cause phosphorylation
of myosin light shear.
Phosphorylation
of the myosin will
interact with actin
and cause contraction
of the vascular
smooth muscle cells.
Calcium calmodulin.
Very, very important.
This is highly
asked in the boards.
So let's start for one
more practical question.
So, you are working
in a scientific
project, which aims
to develop a new
vasodilator that can
replace nitroglycerin.
This new drug will be
used to treat elevated
blood pressure,
hypertensive emergency.
Which of the following
intracellular events
is most likely
responsible for the
beneficial effects of
this new vasodilator?
So, we are looking for
relaxation process.
So, we need to remember
what we need in order
to have not contraction,
but relaxation.
A, actin phosphorylation.
Well,
in vascular smooth
muscle cells,
contraction relaxation
process is not actin
that is phosphorylated.
It's myosin.
And even if the myosin
is phosphorylated,
that's not what we
are looking for.
We are looking for relaxation
process. So, it
cannot be letter A.
Letter B,
calcium release from
sarcoplasmic reticulum.
If we release calcium from
the sarcoplasmic reticulum,
we will have an increase
of calcium intracellular
that will cause contraction.
We don't want that.
Letter C, tyrosine
kinase activation.
No.
D, myosine dephosphorylation.
Yes, because
we know when the myosine
is dephosphorylated,
they will not
interact with actin
anymore, and then we
will have the relaxation.
These are questions
that probably
you can see in the USMLE.
So, again, calcium,
I think we know now,
we are convincing that
calcium is crucial
for the process of
contraction and relaxation
of vascular smooth muscle
cells. Now, we need
understand where this
calcium is coming from
outside the cells inside
the cells or both both
so here we have a
representation of vasculous
movements of cells and all
the channels responsible for
the entry and exit of
calcium in the cells so how
the calcium that's outside
the cells enter the cells
via all these channels
that are represented here
so when those
channels are activated
they open and then
the calcium can enter
so do you need know those
those channels yes mainly
the voltage gated l
-type channel you need to
remember this one, because
when you go to your
pharmacology lectures, you
will learn that there is
a specific drugs that
can block these channels.
And then we have internal
source of calcium.
So the sarcoplasmic
reticulum is a store,
is a place where we
can store calcium.
So, how we can take this
calcium is when
we activate IP3,
IP3 will open specific
channels that are
in the membrane of
sarcoplasmic reticulum,
and the calcium that is
inside of sarcoplasmic
reticulum will go
to the cytoplasma.
if the calcium can enter
the cells if the calcium
from the sarcoplasmic
reticulum can be released
to the cytoplasm should
have a way to remove
the calcium now because
if i don't remove the
calcium i will have
forever contraction in one
point i want a relaxation
so there is a mechanism
where we can remove the
calcium from the cells.
So now let's focus in this
side of the the figure,
calcium exit. So there
is here some pumps,
some channels that we
can remove the calcium.
And this is one of
the most important.
The calcium ATPase channel,
also called CERCA. When
we activate this CERCA,
they take all the
calcium in the cytoplasma
and bring back to the
sarcoplasmatic retina.
so how we can remove calcium
from the cells i just
mentioned right now this
one that's located in
the sarcoplasmic reticulum
is one of the important
one they will take
all the calcium in the
cytoplasma and bring back
to sarcoplasmatic reticulum
but we have some also in
the membrane of vascular
smooth muscle cells. We
have the sodium-calcium
exchanger that will bring
one sodium inside the
cells in exchange with
one release of calcium.
We have also calcium pumps,
but the most important
is cerca, the one
that's located in the
sarcoplasmic reticulum.
so here um i'm just
repeating the process of
vascular smooth muscle
cells relaxation is where we
remove calcium and we
dephosphorylated the myosin
light chain so we remove
the calcium we activate
circa circa will take
all the calcium from the
cytoplasma and store back
to sarcoplasmic reticulum.
So we will have a drop in
the calcium intracellular.
If we don't have a
calcium, we will not have
the formation of calcium
calm modeling process.
So we will not activate
myosin-like chain
kinase and we will not
have the contraction.
So, just as something
astral, because I'm pretty
sure you have this in
pharmacology lectures, but
it's important to know
that, as you saw in the
endothelial cells lecture,
the endothelial cells release
many factors that directly
affect the vascular
smooth muscle cells the
main one nitric oxide but
endothelial cells can
also produce prostacycline
and prostacycline will
cause also vasodilation
in vascular smooth muscle
cells so how that's
happened so when
prostacycline binds to the g
protein receptor in the
vascular smooth muscle cells,
they will convert,
they will activate this
enzyme adenylate cyclase
that will convert ATP and
cyclic AMP, and that
will cause vasodilation.
That is in our learning
objectives that I
think is very important
to discuss is KCL.
You will see a lot
about the effect of
KCL in the heart,
but the effect of KCL
in the vasculature
is very different.
And it's very important
to know how that happened.
So when we apply
KCL in the arteries,
what we observe
is a contraction.
So here's a preparation
that we do in the
lab. We take a piece
of aorta, we place
it in one equipment,
and we apply KCL.
And in minutes, not
minutes, less than
one minute, we see
this huge contraction.
So, how come KCL
can cause vascular
smooth muscle
cells contraction?
So, the solution
that we use, this KCL
solution, is high
concentration of potassium.
We use like 60 millimolar,
that's pretty high. and
that cause a collapse in
the potassium gradient
and that will lead to
depolarization of the cells.
We have depolarization
and then we have influx
of calcium and then the
contraction will happen.
So the sequence is KCl
will cause depolarization
of the membrane
potential and that will
increase the calcium
influx and the contraction.
I know this figure is
very busy, we will not go
through all this, but I
just want to introduce
a very important concept
because that will help
you understand the effect
of calcium blockers
when you go to your
pharmacological learning.
So here we have a
representation of
vascularized muscle cells
when we give K-cell.
We have depolarization
and then the calcium
that is astrocellular
will enter the cells.
So what that shows
us is if I want to
avoid, if I want to
block contraction,
what is the approach
I can use? I can try
block the channels that
will make the calcium
enter the cells, and
that's exactly what some
scientists has done in
the past. They found
that if we can block
these calcium channels,
the calcium will not enter, and
that will prevent contraction.
So, here are some examples
of L-type calcium blocker,
nifedipine, amilodipine,
verapamil. This is
all drugs that are
used in treatments like
hypertension, where you want
to decrease vasoconstriction.
so it's possible
we can block the
entering of calcium
in the cells.
So calcium is crucial in
contraction not only of the
smooth muscle cells but
cardiac and skeletal muscle.
But there is just
one very specific
mechanism that you need to know
and I will describe
here very briefly.
So, calcium is important that
we, I think, are convincing,
So, when we have
depolarization of muscle cells,
that will cause activation
of the L-type calcium
channel that is located
in the membrane of the
cells, and that will increase
intracellular calcium.
This calcium will bind to
troponin in the cardiac
muscle or calmodulin
in the smooth muscle.
and the contractile
process will happen.
But there is just
one very curious
thing that happened
in the cardiac
muscle and smooth
muscle and didn't and
don't happen in the
skeletal muscle.
So in the skeletal muscle you
see here the calcium channel
that they will activate
another receptor in the
sarcoplasmic reticulum
and release the calcium
from the sarcoplasmic
reticulum to the cytoplasm.
The difference about smooth
muscle, cardiac muscle,
and the skeletal muscle is
that the skeletal muscle,
you have the release
of calcium from the
sarcoplasmic reticulum,
but that doesn't
need an influx of
calcium. If you look here
we need calcium to
enter the cells first
to stimulate this receptor
and release more calcium.
So the skeletal
muscle they will have
the contraction but
without significant
influx of calcium.
You don't need
the calcium from
outside the cell.
Because the skeletal
muscle is not depending on
extracellular calcium
influx, channel blockers like
verapamil do not affect
skeletal muscle contactility.
The reason we are discussing
this is because when you
start to study those drugs,
L-type calcium channel,
they will have effect in
the contractile process,
only in the heart
and the smooth muscle
cells. They will not have
effect in the skeletal
muscle, because remember,
the skeletal muscle
don't need the calcium,
the influx of calcium.
Ah, but how about these
drugs? They can block this
receptor that is in the
sarcoplasmic reticulum? No.
There is no drug yet
that can block this.
These drugs block the calcium
channels in the membrane
of the cells, not in the
sarcoplasmic reticulum.
And finally, every
time I teach about the
vasculous movements of
cells relaxation, I cannot
not discuss about sodium
nitroprusite because
this drug you will see
a lot in your products.
So this is a drug that's
considered a
nitric oxide donor.
And what is unique about
this drug is that this
drug can activate its mood
muscle cells directly.
The effect is independent
of endothelial cells.
So this drug is a nitric
oxide donor. So they will
activate the guanylucyclase
enzyme that will convert
to GTP and cyclic GMP
and cause the relaxation.
That's happened independent
of endothelial cells.
So let's imagine one
case of diabetic patients
that have a red
endothelial dysfunction.
And for any reason,
this patient need to
be vasodilated in an
emergency situation.
So this is the drug
that has been used
a lot in the ER for
hypertensive crisis.
is a very potent
vasodilator, and they act
directly in the vascular
smooth muscle cells.
This is independent
of endothelial cells.
So, vasodilation can
occur in two manners,
endothelial-dependent or
endothelial-independent.
So, here is one example
where vascular smooth
muscle cells can relax
and cause waste dilation
independent of endothelial
cells, independent of
nitric oxide coming from
the endothelial cells.
So, as a summary of this
lecture, we discuss about
contractile proteins, the
importance of calcium,
carol modulin process,
phosphorylation of the myosin,
dephosphorylation of myosin,
source of calcium, how
we can remove the calcium
from the cells, and we touch
base a little bit on the
effect of nitroprusside and
causing relaxation of
vascularized muscle cells, and
KCL causing contraction of
vascularized muscle cells.
That's all for this
lecture. If there is
something, some
concepts that you would
like to discuss more
or you have some
questions, please reach
out to me via email.
And that's all for
today. Thank you.